I'll be going through the initial camera calibration steps
我准备在这个 Jupyter Notebook 中
in this Jupyter notebook.
演示一遍镜头校准的流程
The first step will be to read in calibration images of a chessboard.
第一步是读取用于标定的多张棋盘图像
it's recommended to use at least 20 images to get a reliable calibration.
建议使用至少 20 张图像 以实现可靠的校准
And for this example,
在这个例子里
we have a lot of images in this calibration images folder.
该文件夹中有多张校准图像
They are all images of a chessboard, taken at different angles and distances.
它们都是同一个棋盘的图像 只是拍摄角度和距离不一样
And there's also a test image. I'll eventually want to test my
此外 还有一幅检测图像 最后我们需要检测
camera calibration and undistortion on.
相机校准的效果 并去除该检测图像中的畸变
Each chessboard here has eight by six corners to detect.
在每幅棋盘图像中可以检测到 8×6 个角点
I'll go through the calibration steps for
我将详细讲解
the first calibration image in detail.
第一张图像的校准步骤
First, you can see that I've already done my Numpy OpenCV and
首先 你能看到我已经导入了 Numpy OpenCV
plotting imports.
和用于绘图的库
Then I'll read in the first image calibration1.jpg, and I'll display it.
接下来 读取 calibration1.jpg 并显示这张图片
So here's our calibration image.
这就是我们的校准图像
I'll map the coordinates of the corners in this 2D image,
我会把这张二维图像中的角点（称为image points）的坐标
which I'll call it's image points, to the 3D coordinates of the real,
与真实 没有畸变的棋盘图上对应点（称为object points）的坐标
undistorted chessboard corners, which I'll call object points.
一一对应起来
So, I'll set up two empty arrays to hold these points, object points and
接下来 我将定义两个空数组来保存这些点
image points.
包括对象点（object points）和图像点（image points）
The object points will all be the same.
对象点保持不动
Just the known object coordinates of the chessboard corners for
它们就是 8×6 的棋盘上
an eight by six board.
已知角点的坐标
These points will be 3D coordinates, x, y and z from the top left corner,
这些点都是三维坐标 从最左上角的 0,0,0 开始
0, 0, 0, to the bottom right, 7, 5, 0.
到最右下角的 7,5,0 结束
The z coordinate will be zero for
每个点的 z 坐标都为零
every point, since the board is on a flat image plane.
因为棋盘是放置在一个扁平的图像平面上的
And x and y will be all the coordinates of the corners.
x 和 y 坐标是这些角点的所有坐标
So I'll prepare these object points,
下面 我将准备这些对象点
first by creating six by eight points in an array.
首先在数组中创建 6×8 个点
Each with three columns for the x, y, and z coordinates of each corner.
每个点都有三列数据 即每个点的 x、y 和 z 坐标
I'll initialize these all as zeros using Numpy's zero function.
我将试用 Numpy 的 zero 函数将这些坐标点都初始化为零
The z coordinate will stay zero so I'll leave that as it is but for
z 坐标将保持为零 无需变动
our first two columns, x and y
不过对于前两列数据 即 x、y 坐标
I'll use Numpy's mgrid function to generate the coordinates that I want.
我将使用 Numpy 的 mgrid 函数生成我想要的坐标值
mgrid returns the coordinate values for a given grid size and
mgrid 的返回值是给定网格大小的坐标值
I'll shape those coordinates back into two columns, one for x and one for y.
我将这些坐标值重新排列为两列的形式 一列为坐标 x 另一列为 y 坐标
Next, to create the image points, I want to look
接下来 为了新建图像点
at the distorted calibration image and detect the corners of the board.
需要查看失真的校准图像并检测棋盘的角点
OpenCV gives us an easy way to detect chessboard corners with a function
OpenCV 可让我们轻松地检测到棋盘角点
called findChessboardCorners that returns the corners
它提供了一个名为 findChessboardCorners 的函数
found in a grayscale image.
该函数可返回在灰度图像中检测到的角点
So I'll convert this image to greyscale and
因此，我先把这个图像转为灰度图像
then I'll pass that into the findChessboardCorners function.
然后将其作为 findChessboardCorners 函数的参数传入
This takes in our greyscale image along with the dimensions of the chessboard
同时传入地还有图像中每行每列
corners.
角点的个数
In this case, eight by six, and the last parameter is for any flags.
在本例中 角点个数为 8×6，最后一个参数用于传入一些操作标记
And there are none in this example.
在这个例子不需要传入任何标记
If this function detects corners,
每当函数检测到角点
I'll append those points to the image points array.
就把这些点添加到存放图像点的数组中
I'll also add our prepared object points,
我还会把已经准备好的对象点（变量名为 objp）
objp, to the object points array.
相应地添加到对象点的数组中
And these object points will be the same for
对所有的校准图像而言 这些对象点都是相同的
all of the calibration images, since they represent a real chessboard.
因为它们代表的是同一个真实的棋盘
Next, I'll also draw the detected corners,
接下来 我在图像上标记出检测到的角点
with a call to drawChessboardCorners,
具体做法是 调用 drawChessboardCorners 函数
that takes in our image, corner dimensions and corner points.
该函数接受目标图像、角点个数和角点坐标作为参数
And I'll display these corners so
我把这些角点展示出来
that we can see what was detected in an interactive window.
让大家在交互窗口中看到检测结果
So let's run this code.
下面来运行这段代码
Here's what our detected corners look like.
这就是所检测到的角点的样子
And if I zoom in, it looks like the corners were detected pretty accurately.
放大之后 可以看到这些角点的检测似乎非常准确
The next step will be to do this for all the calibration images.
接下来 我们对所有校准图像重复上述步骤
I can read in all the calibration images by importing the glob API,
我可以导入 glob  API 从而读入所有的校准图像
which helps read in images with a consistent file name,
该 API 可帮助导入文件名比较一致的图像
like calibration one, two, three, and so on.
例如 校准图像1、校准图像2、校准图像3 等等
Then, I'll iterate through each image file, detecting corners and
然后我将遍历每个图像文件 检测出角点
appending points to the object and image points arrays.
并将这些角点分别添加到对象点和图像点对应的数组中
Then later, we'll be able to use the object points and
然后 我们将使用这些对象点和
image points to calibrate this camera.
图像点来校准摄像头
I'll show you the OpenCV functions you'll need to calibrate the camera and
下面 我来讲解进行相机标定和图像正畸
finally, undistort images.
所涉及的 OpenCV 函数
To calibrate a camera, OpenCV gives us the calibrateCamera function.
如需标定镜头  可以使用 OpenCV 提供的 calibrateCamera 函数
This takes in our object points, our image points, and
该函数的入参包括对象点坐标 图像点坐标
the shape of the image.
以及图像的尺寸
And using these inputs, it calculates and
利用这些输入参数 该函数可计算并
returns the distortion coefficients and the camera matrix that we need
返回失真系数矩阵以及相机矩阵
to transform 3D object points to 2D image points.
它们会帮助我们将三维的对象点转换为二维的图像点
It also returns the position of the camera in the world, with values for
该函数还会返回相机在世界坐标系中的位置
rotation and translation vectors.
包括旋转向量和平移向量
The next function you'll need is undistort.
下一个函数是 undistort
This takes in a distorted image, our camera matrix, and
该函数的入参是一幅畸变的图像 相机矩阵和
distortion coefficients.
失真系数矩阵
And it returns an undistorted, often called destination image.
它的返回值是矫正后的图像 通常称之为目标图像
In the next quiz, you'll need to apply what you've learned to calibrate
在接下来的小测验中 你将使用你所学到的知识
the camera and correct for image distortion.
对相机进行标定并去除图像中的畸变
Good luck.
祝你好运！